{"tossups": [{"question": "A shipment of arms to this group aboard the<em> Eksund</em> was intercepted by the French and discovered to have been sent by Muammar Gaddafi. Bobby Sands died in a hunger strike protesting the prison rights afforded to members of this group, which began to disarm after Sinn Fein [shin fayn] signed the Good Friday Accords with Tony Blair. For ten points, name this paramilitary group that split off from an\u201cOfficial\u201d nonviolent group shortly after \u201cThe Troubles\u201d began in Ireland.", "answer": "<b> Provisional Irish Republican Army</b> (or<b> PIRA</b>; prompt on Irish Republican Army or IRA alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s end was hastened by the intervention of George Snowden\u2019s militia, despite William McCleary\u2019s numerous attempts at peaceful negotiation. Alexander Berkman\u2019s attempt to assassinate a participant in this event brought it into the national spotlight. A group attempting to stop this event was caught while traveling in barges up the Ohio River. Pinkerton agents working for Henry Clay Frick failed to break, for ten points, what 1892 strike of Pennsylvania steelworkers at a Carnegie plant?", "answer": "<b> Homestead</b> Steel strike", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man wrote an analysis of the German psyche after World War II titled<em> Anti-Semite and Jew</em>. This first editor of the journal<em> Modern Times</em> popularized the phrase \u201cexistence precedes essence\u201d in his<em> Existentialism and Humanism</em>, which rejected deterministic excuses for behavior. This philosopher popularized the idea that there are \u201ctwo modes of consciousness,\u201d and that \u201cbad faith\u201d forces human beings to adopt false values, in his<em> Being and Nothingness</em>. For ten points, name this French post-war philosopher and Nobel Laureate who was married to Simone de Beauvoir.", "answer": "Jean-Paul<b> Sartre</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A member of this family was targeted by the Soviet-backed Yanan Faction in the \u201cSecond Arduous March.\u201d This family is honored on the \u201cDay of the Sun.\u201d A member of this family instituted the \u201cJuche\u201d[joo-chay] policy of self-reliance and took the title of \u201cEternal President,\u201d while another member of this family allegedly ordered a hacking of Sony after he was unfavorably depicted in<em> The Interview.</em> Il-Sung, Jong-Il, and Jong-Un are members of, for ten points, what family that rules North Korea?", "answer": "<b> Kim</b> family", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This scientist discovered that stereoisomers of tartaric acid rotate polarized light in opposite directions. He saved the silk industry in his country by determining that silkworms were dying from an infectious disease called flacherie. This scientist was able to save Joseph Meister from a dog bite due to his research into a vaccine for rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process removes harmful microorganisms from milk.", "answer": "Louis<b> Pasteur</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "Major cities in this country were seized by Yahya Khan\u2019s troops during Operation Searchlight in an attempt to prevent the Awami League from taking power. In 1971, George Harrison organized the world\u2019s first benefit concert to support this country, which was suffering a genocide during its war of independence from Pakistan. For ten points, name this country, now an independent country with capital Dhaka.", "answer": "<b> Bangladesh</b> (accept Concert for<b> Bangladesh</b>; prompt on East Pakistan)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "As a result of this treaty, Portugal regained Colonia do Sacramento in Uruguay. This treaty forced North American tribes formerly loyal to France to open trade with all nations. Britain increased its hold on the slave market when it was given the<em> asiento</em>, along with Gibraltar, in this treaty. Philip, duke of Anjou, renounced his claim to the French throne as a result of, for ten points, what treaty that ended the War of the Spanish Succession?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Utrecht</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This river was the subject of the Pick-Sloan plan, which sought to build the Garrison and Fort Peck Dams. Fort Mandan was built along the banks of this river as a wintering spot for a 1804-1805 expedition; that expedition, led by Lewis and Clark, traversed the entire length of this river, which flows past Omaha and Kansas City. For ten points, name this longest tributary of the Mississippi River, which joins it north of St. Louis.", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The instigators of this battle intended to start the assault shortly after the delivery of the Fourteen Part Message. A pilot who crash landed during this battle received support and animosity from the local populace in the Niihau Incident. Wheeler Air Field was repeatedly targeted in this battle, which controversially did not include a third wave of striking aircraft. For ten points, name this 1941 battle in which the USS<em> Arizona</em> was sunk.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Pearl Harbor</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The losing side of this war used an encirclement technique called<em> motti</em>. The winners of this war were able to lease a naval base at Hanko and occupy the city of Vyborg. Its victors suffered heavy losses due to the effects of the Great Purge. The losers were forced to cede Karelia after the fall of the Mannerheim Line, despite the use of ski troops. The Continuation War followed, for ten points, what conflict between Finland and the Soviet Union, simultaneous with the start of World War II?", "answer": "<b> Winter</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This country controls an archipelago with capital Funchal that is known for a variety of fortified wine. This country\u2019s second-largest city sits at the mouth of the Douro River and lends its name to another fortified wine. This country transferred control of its Macau colony to China in 1999. Porto and the Madeiras are found in this nation, which is largely coextensive with the Roman province of Lusitania. For ten points, name this country with capital at Lisbon, which shares the Iberian Peninsula with Spain.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b> (or<b> Portuguese Republic</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A man nicknamed after this animal, Charles Jones, worked with Charles Goodnight in a conservation effort to preserve their numbers. Another man nicknamed for this animal called his rifle Lucretia Borgia and once killed over sixty of these animals in an eight-hour hunting competition. The 10th Cavalry bore a nickname referencing this animal, a term eventually applied to several African-American regiments. William Cody\u2019s nickname was that of, for ten points, what animal, whose population plummeted as American settlers traveled west?", "answer": "<b> buffalo</b> (accept<b> bison</b>; accept<b> Buffalo</b> Bill; accept<b> Buffalo</b> Soldiers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "As part of this event, the Meirokusha society promoted \u201ccivilization and enlightenment.\u201d Laws enacted during this period included tax reform that returned land to the government and the replacement of the <em>han</em> system with prefectures. A group of reforms during this period were outlined in the Charter Oath. In this period, a group of daimyo fought the Boshin War against the government, and the Satsuma Rebellion was launched by discontented samurai. For ten points, name this period of 19th century modernization in Japan in which the emperor was restored to power.", "answer": "<b> Meiji</b> Restoration (accept equivalents for restoration; accept descriptions of the<b> Meiji</b> era or government)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man began his \u201cNew Course\u201d by appointing Leo von Caprivi as chancellor. He flew into a rage during an interview with the<em> Daily Telegraph</em> and sent the gunboat<em> Panther</em> to start the Agadir Crisis. This man replaced Helmuth von Moltke the Younger with Erich von Falkenhayn after the failure of the Schlieffen Plan. This grandson of Victoria supported Austria after the death of Franz Ferdinand and dismissed Otto von Bismarck. For ten points, name this last Kaiser of Germany, who ruled during World War I.", "answer": "<b> Wilhelm II</b> (or<b> William II</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man briefly suspended one campaign on<em> Larry King Live</em>. This man\u2019s running mate asked \u201cWho am I? Why am I here?\u201d in a vice-presidential debate. Admiral James Stockdale ran with this founder of Electronic Data Systems, who used charts to advocate for a balanced budget and briefly led both George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton in polling. For ten points, name this Texas businessman who founded the Reform Party and won nineteen percent of the popular vote in the 1992 election.", "answer": "(Henry) Ross<b> Perot</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The first Boeing 747 to suffer an accident was this airline\u2019s Flight 540 in 1974; 55 people died in Kenya in its worst disaster. In 1977, one of this airline\u2019s planes was stormed by members of GSG 9, ending a hostage crisis by Palestinian hijackers who wanted the release</b> <b>of members of the Red Army (+)</b> <b>Faction. In 1972, another of this airline\u2019s planes was</b> <b>hijacked, leading to the release of three members of Black September who committed the Munich massacre. (*)</b> Cologne serves as headquarters for, for ten points, what largest German airline?", "answer": "Deutsche<b> Lufthansa</b> AG", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This artist designed stained glass in memory of Dag Hammerskj\u00a8old for the United Nations</b> <b>Headquarters dedicated to Peace. He used a Cubist style to show a (+)</b> <b>purple-coated</b> <b>violinist standing on top of two houses, based off his childhood in a Hasidic community. At the top of one painting, he included a woman playing the violin upside-down and a (*) </b>green-skinned man holding a glowing tree while facing a farm animal. For ten points, name this Russian painter of<em> I and the Village</em>.", "answer": "Marc<b> Chagall</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This work informs listeners that \u201cthey shall be left to fall as they are inclined by their own weight\u201d when discussing a passage that notes \u201cTheir foot shall slide in due time\u201d from Deuteronomy. The image of a (+) spider dangling over a pit of fire is invoked in this work, which warned listeners that \u201cthere is nothing that keeps wicked men [...] out of (*)</b> hell, but the mere pleasure of God.\u201d For ten points, name this fearsome sermon, a powerful example of the first Great Awakening, delivered in 1741 by Jonathan Edwards.", "answer": "<b> Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Johannes Ockeghem wrote the first surviving polyphonic example of this composition. Berlioz wrote one of these pieces with four brass bands to commemorate the July Revolution.</b> <b>These pieces normally feature a (+)</b> <b>hymn attributed to Thomas of Celano. Another of</b> <b>these pieces includes a trombone solo in its \u201cTuba Mirum\u201d section and was completed by Franz (*)</b> Sussmayr after its composer died while working on its \u201cLacrimosa.\u201d A \u201cDies Irae\u201d is usually found in, for ten points, what type of composition that was Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart\u2019s last, a mass for the dead?", "answer": "<b> requiem</b>s (or requiem mass)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>After this man\u2019s citizen militia fled, the Spanish sacked the city of Prato in 1512, ending the rule of Piero Soderini. This man wrote that \u201cbecause Fortune is a (+) woman, one must thrash her to have one\u2019s way with her,\u201d and he discussed the first 10 books of the</b><em><b> History </b><b>of Rome</b></em><b> in his</b><em><b> Discourses on Livy</b></em><b>. Another work by this author views Cesare Borgia as a model (*) </b> ruler, claims that it is better to be feared than to be loved. and was dedicated to Lorenzo d\u2019Medici. For ten points, name this Italian author of<em> The Prince</em>.", "answer": "Niccol\u00b4o<b> Machiavelli</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Era of Good Feelings was led by, for ten points, what President who protected Latin America from European interference with a famous doctrine?", "answer": "James<b> Monroe</b> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One instance of this action was caused when someone threw a brick at a crowd</b> <b>led by Jan Zelivsky; Wenceslaus IV died of shock after hearing about that event. In</b> <b>another instance of this action, Vilem Slavata and Jaroslav Martinitz were (+) saved,</b> <b>according to enemy Protestants, by a pile of horse manure; that instance of this action</b> <b>occurred after the violation of the Letter of Majesty, which helped start the (*)</b> Thirty Years War. For ten points, name this violent action that took place in 1419 and 1618 in Prague, involving political opponents being thrown out of a window.", "answer": "(First and/or Second)<b> defenestration</b>s of Prague (prompt on descriptive answers relating to \u201cbeing thrown out of a window\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}